Aseem Srivastava PhD Scholar at LCS2 Lab, IIIT Delhi, India

☑ as3eem.github.io ② aseems@iiitd.ac.in

Presearch Block, IIIT Delhi, India □ +91 8736977760

A fourth-year PhD student at IIIT Delhi, currently under the guidance of Dr. Md. Shad Akhtar and Dr. Tanmoy Chakraborty at LCS2 Lab, India. My research interest is in NLP/Deep Learning for Dialogue Systems, with a specialized focus on improvising conversational mental health assistants. I specialize in applying large language models (LLMs) and LLMOps for dialogue and behavioral understanding and encourage open sourcing with production-ready research.

Education

Indraprastha Institute of Information Technology (IIIT Delhi), Delhi

2020 - PRESENT

PhD in Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) | CGPA: 8.53

Thesis: Building Blocks of Dialogue System for Effective Virtual Mental Health Assistants

Supervisor: Dr. Md. Shad Akhtar & Dr. Tanmoy Chakraborty

KAMLA NEHRU INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY (KNIT), SULTANPUR

2016 - 2020

B.Tech in Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) | Agg: 68.3%

Thesis: Amazon Review Analysis to Guage User Sentiments

Publications

JMIR MH

Exploring the Efficacy of LLMs in Summarizing Counseling Sessions: A Benchmark Study

2024

Prottay Kumar Adhikary, Aseem Srivastava, Shivani Kumar, Salam Michael Singh, Puneet Manuja, Jini K Gopinath, Vijay Krishnan, Swati Kedia, Koushik Sinha Deb, Tanmoy Chakraborty

[LLM] [GenerativeAl]

The Web Conf

Response-act Guided Reinforced Dialogue Generation for Mental Health Counseling

2023

Aseem Srivastava, Ishan Pandey, Md. Shad Akhtar, Tanmoy Chakraborty

Transformer Reinforcement Learning | GenerativeAl | Controlled Generation |

KDD 2022

Counseling Summarization using Mental Health Knowledge Guided Utterance Filtering

Aseem Srivastava, Tharun Suresh, Grin Lord, Md. Shad Akhtar, Tanmoy Chakraborty

[LLM] Knowledge Infusion | Controlled Generation |

ICWSM 2022

A Computational Approach to Understand Mental Health from Reddit: Knowledge-aware Multitask Learning Framework

Usha Lokala, Aseem Srivastava, Triyasha Ghosh Dastidar, Tanmoy Chakraborty, Md Shad Akthar, Maryam Panahiazar, Amit Sheth

Transformers Reddit Mental Health Knowledge Infusion

WSDM 2022

Speaker and Time-aware Joint Contextual Learning for Dialogue-act Classification in Counselling

Ganeshan Malhotra, Abdul Waheed, Aseem Srivastava, Md. Shad Akhtar, Tanmoy Chakraborty

Transformers Joint Learning

Under Review

- > Knowledge Planning in Large Language Models for Domain-Aligned Dialogue Summarization [EMNLP]
- > Knowledge-infused Hierarchy-aware Emotion Recognition in Code-mixed Mental Health Counseling Conversations [EMNLP]
- > Sentiment-guided Commonsense-aware Response Generation for Counseling [Affective Computing]
- > Critical Behavioral Traits Foster Peer Engagement in Online Reddit Communities [PlosONE]

Skills

Interests NLP - Dialogue Systems, Deep Learning, Machine Learning, Human Behavior, GenAl, LLMs Technical Data Structures and Algorithms, Python, PyTorch, LLMOps, Tensorflow, Git, Cloud Services NodeJS, Flutter, MySQL, NoSQL

LAST UPDATED: JULY 4, 2024 ASEEM SRIVASTAVA - CV 1

Experience

RESEARCH INTERN AUGUST 2022 - JANUARY 2023

Mpathic | USA (Remote)

Undertook research statement around NLP and dialogue summarization tailored for counseling. I led the development of an end-to-end pipeline, crafting a novel methodology from scratch and overseeing its implementation for in-house deployment, including optimizing team workflows. Our research findings were published at KDD 2022 (A* conference).

LLMs AWS

Data Science Intern

July 2019 - August 2019

Analytics Vidhya | Gurgaon, India

Spearheaded the development of machine learning and deep learning models for an in-house portal. In addition, we worked with a team to enhance our understanding of deep neural networks to facilitate better recommendation frameworks.

Machine Learning Deep Learning Text Analytics

Organized Tutorials & Workshops

ICON 2023

Building Blocks of AI-Driven Mental Health Counseling

(Tutorial) | Organizers : Aseem Srivastava, Neeraj, Yash Kumar Atri, Shivani Kumar, Shad Akhtar, Tanmoy Chakraborty

Invited Talks & Symposiums

[Symposiums]

> Google Research Week 2023 & 2024 – Got two back to back invitations to attend and present our work at Research Week with Google, India.

[Talks]

- > ACM ARCS 2024 Got invited by ACM India to present a lightning talk and our work on dialogue response generation in NISER Bhubhneshwar.
- > Cord.Al 2023 Got invited to present a talk on Role of Conversational Agent's Component in Digital Counseling.

Position of Responsibility

- 2024 Serving as Program Committee member at ASONAM 2024, Italy.
- Leading an open-source community of 500+ like-minded enthusiasts to encourage awareness and know-ledge of Deep Learning for NLP.
- 2022 Served as Web Chair at International Conference on Natural Language Processing (ICON) 2022, India.
- 2022 Served as Web Chair at CONSTRAINT Workshop (co-located w/ ACL 2022).
- 2021 Served as a volunteer at notable conferences, including KDD, ACL, AAAI, COLING, and WSDM.

Achievements

- 2023 Received Google Research Grant to present our WWW '23 paper in Austin, USA.
- 2022 Received ACM India Grant to present our KDD '22 paper in Washington DC, USA.
- 2019 Placed in the top 9% (N=8000) of the leaderboard in IIT-M Alumni Association Hackearth's machine learning challenge with an accuracy of 99.63%.
- 2018 Runners up in Facebook's Digital Hackathon for creating an social web platform and won INR 40,000.

References

Dr. Md. Shad Akhtar

Assistant Professor, IIIT Delhi (shad.akhtar@iiitd.ac.in)

Dr. Tanmoy Chakraborty

Associate Professor, IIT Delhi (chak.tanmoy.iit@gmail.com)

2